Guide to the Records of The New York Institute for the Humanities RG.37.4
New York University Archives
- Series III. Audio and Video Recordings, 1974-2010
  - Subseries IIIA. Cassette Tapes, 1974-2005
    - Meeting on Urban Development, with Saskia Sassen, Undated; cuid4144; 1 audiocassettes 36:16; Tape label "Sassen-Koob Nov. 30"
      This appears to be a recording of a meeting of people discussing urban development in New York City. Saskia Sassen-Koob is among the people present. The meeting closes by one of the participants listing a number of other groups in the City interested in urban issues and holding meetings in upcoming weeks.
      Community development, Urban; Sassen, Saskia
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 38)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:17)
    - The Hebrew Political Poetry of Aharon Shabtai and English Translations by Peter Cole -- Readings and Discussion with the Author and Translator, Undated; cuid4145; 1 audiocassettes Approx 70 minutes
      Israeli poet Aharon Shabtai discusses political poetry. Peter Cole discusses translating the poems into English. Cole and Shabtai read the poems both in Hebrew and English and then discuss.
      Hebrew poetry; Israeli poetry; Hebrew poetry, Modern; Cole, Peter, 1957- Poems. Selections; Shabtai, Aharon. Poems. Selections. English; Protest poetry, Hebrew; Cole, Peter, 1957-; Shabtai, Aharon
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 39)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:18)
    - Harvard GSD (Graduate School of Design) Conference. Talks by Moshe Safdie, Teddy Kollek, and Richard Sennet, Undated; cuid4146; 1 audiocassettes Approx 60 minutes; Microphone is far from the speakers causing audio problems. The person recording the conference says the name of each speaker into the mic at the beginning of their talks, introducing them.
      Three talks by various speakers at the Harvard Graduate School of Design Conference of an unknown year. Talks by Moshe Safdie, Teddy Kollek and Richard Sennett.
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 40)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:19)
    - Discussion of the Equal Rights Amendment of 1972. New Right Seminar, Undated; cuid4147; 1 audiocassettes; Tape Label: New Right Seminar 9/25
      Barbara Ehrenreich and Allen Hunter act as "co-conveners" of this New Right Seminar on the Equal Rights Amendment of 1972 and how the political right reacted to it.
      Equal rights amendments; Conservatism; New Right; Hunter, Allen, 1944-; Ehrenreich, Barbara
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 41)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:20-8:21)
    - Untitled Lecture by Richard Rorty, Undated; cuid4148; 1 audiocassettes Approx 80 minutes
      Richard Rorty talks for 78 minutes, discussing, among other things, truth, knowledge, science, values, ethics, moral philosophy language and human cognitive capacity.
      Rorty, Richard
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 42)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:22)
    - Einstein and Religion Biography Seminar, Undated; cuid4149; 1 audiocassettes; Tape label: Biography seminar 5/20
      Unidentified speaker discusses Albert Einstein and religion, followed by Q&A. The title of the talk seems to be based on the Einstein quote, "The Lord God is subtle, but malicious he is not."
      Astrophysics; Mathematical physics; Physics |x Social aspects.; Physics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Religion; Spinoza, Benedictus de, 1632-1677; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 43)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:23)
    - The Use of Narrative in Historical Writing. A Conversation with Tom Bender, Undated; cuid4150; 1 audiocassettes; Tape is labeled "Friday lunch 11/7 Tom Bender Culture + the City." Recording is quite loud, with audio clipping at some points.
      Thomas Bender leads a conversation (and Q&A) about the use of narrative in historical writing. He bases his talk on the relationship between the history of cities and cultural history.
      narrative structure; Writing history; Bender, Thomas, 1944-
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 45)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:24)
    - Authority Conference: A Three-Day Discourse on Production and the Division of Labor, February 24-26, 1978; cuid4151; 4 audiocassettes Approx. 6 hours; This event was recorded on twelve sides of six audiocassettes. Each session comprises three sides, thus each session is split between two tapes, combined with a subsequent session on one of them. Two tapes are missing - they would be tapes 4 and 5 in the series of 6, containing all of session 3 and the first part of session 4. It is hoped that these tapes will reveal themselves during the digitization process. During recording, the microphone was frequently jostled or bumped up and down, causing a constant bumping sound on several of the tapes.
      Because of the piecemeal manner in which the tapes comprising this conference have been digitized, each tape previously had its own unique identifier. The preservation masters will be labeled by these unique IDs. They are as follows:
      Tape 1: RG37-4_ref2332 Tape 2: RG37-4_ref2300 Tape 3: RG37-4_ref2308 Tape 4: still unknown Tape 5: still unknown Tape 6: RG37-4_ref2303
      Historical note
      The Authority Conference brought approximately 20 humanistic scholars together in order to discuss authority, production, and the division of labor and how those topics are treated in thought, theory, and practice in various humanities fields. Intellectual goals stated in a letter of invitation were to better "understand how the productive processes of modern society are changing in ways not anticipated in past social theory" and to "expand the meaning of the term 'production' itself, so that it appears as a cultural, psychological, and epistemological category as well as a category in political economy." The final desired outcome of the conference was to set up an ongoing working group to pursue whatever develops during the sessions.
      Session 1: "The Production of Meaning" lead by Anthony Giddens and Bernard Williams. Session 2: "The Economic and Psychological Conflicts in the Division of Labor" lead by Dick Sennett and Bob Solow. Session 3: TAPES MISSING "On Emerging Conflicts in Patterns of Authority in Modern Capitalism" lead by Claus Offe and Elizabeth Hegeman, summarized by Alessandro Pizzorno. Session 4: PART 1 MISSING - Conference Wrap Up/Next Steps.
      Session 1.1: ACCESS 11:06 (shared university archives box 114) Session 1.2: ACCESS 11:07 (shared university archives box 114) Session 1.3: ACCESS 8:26 (shared university archives box 111) Session 2.1: ACCESS 8:25 (shared university archives box 111) Session 2.2-2.3: ACCESS 10:02 (shared university archives box 113) Session 3.1-3.3: TAPES MISSING - NO ACCESS COPY Session 4.1: TAPE MISSING - NO ACCESS COPY Session 4.2-4.3: ACCESS 8:30 (shared university archives box 111)
      Authority; Division of labor; Economic development.; Capitalism.; Production control; Production functions (Economic theory); Labor supply.; Ford Foundation; Hirschman, Albert O.; Gendlin, Eugene T., 1926-2017; Giddens, Anthony; Hegeman, Elizabeth; Kohn, Melvin L., 1928-; Morgenbesser, Sidney, 1921-2004; Nagel, Thomas, 1937-; Offe, Claus; Piore, Michael J.; Bickford, Jane; Williams, Bernard, 1929-2003; Zuboff, Shoshana, 1951-; Solow, Robert M.; Unger, Roberto Mangabeira; Skinner, Quentin; Smith, Jonathan Z.; Schrank, Robert, 1917-; Sennett, Richard, 1943-; Rollings, Andrew E.; Sabel, Charles F.; Berger, Suzanne E., 1944-; Pizzorno, Alessandro; Frampton, Kenneth; Birnbaum, Norman; Garfinkel, Harold; Freidson, Eliot, 1923-2005
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 46)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:25-8:26, 8:30)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:2)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 114, Cd 11:6-11:7)
    - Equality, Opportunity and Capability. A Discussion with Amartya Sen, Undated; cuid4152; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes; Tape Label: 11/16 Amartya Sen Lunch Tape 1
      Amartya Sen discusses freedom, equality, opportunity and capability.
      Opportunity; capability; Equality; Freedom; Sen, Amartya, 1933-
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 47)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:27-8:28)
    - Youth, Race, and Poverty: On Downward Mobility in America. A Lecture by William Finnegan, April 5, 1996; cuid4153; 1 audiocassettes Approx 65 minutes
      New York Times staff writer William Finnegan discusses the topic of a book in progress - youth, race and poverty in America and the trend of downward mobility. Before Finnegan's lecture, Charles Halpern eulogizes W. Hayword Burns, who had been killed in an automobile accident the previous Tuesday.
      Children of minorities; Youth with social disabilities; Youth.; downward mobility; Poverty.; Ethnic groups.; Finnegan, William
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 48)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 111, Cd 8:29)
    - Gustave Flaubert Discussion Group, circa 1972-1982; cuid4154; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes
      This is a recording of a discussiong group engaging in conversation about the works of Gustave Flaubert, focusing on A Sentimental Education in particular. The recording begins without introduction or preamble. The first several minutes are people arriving and chatting. The only person to be identified in the recording, by way of being greeted is a man hailed as "Professor Falk." The discussion begins at about 9:50, with one participant reading a passage from Sentimental Education.
      While the recording is undated, the cassette itself can be dated to 1972-75, based on information taken from the packaging. The C-90 was introduced in 1972 and distributed in the US by Superscope until 1975.
      Recorded on both sides of a Sony C-90 High Fidelity 90 minute auto-sensor low-noise audiocassette (Distributed by Superscope, Sunvalley, California).
      Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880. Education sentimentale. English; Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 50)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:50-9:51)
    - The Philosophy of Karl Popper. A Conversation with Jonathan Lieberson, circa 1982-1983; cuid4155; 1 audiocassettes 20:19; Tape labeled "J Liebersohn [sic] lunch on Popper"
      Side 2 is blank
      Scholar and author Jonathan Lieberson discusses the philosophy of Karl Popper, focusing on, among other topics, objectivity vs. subjectivity, reification and subjective investments.
      Philosophy; Popper, Karl R. (Karl Raimund), 1902-1994; Lieberson, Jonathan
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 51)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:52)
    - Post-911 Israeli/Palestinian Relations, circa March 2003; cuid4156; 1 audiocassettes Approx 90 minutes; Tape is labeled "NYIH Internal seminar" and has a Star of David drawn next to that text. Severe electronic hum heard throught on both sides. This was part of the original recording.
      The moderator introduces the speaker as "Nissim," the author of five books and the editor of a Hebrew critical journal. The speaker is likely Nissim Mishal, a prominent Israeli author and journalist. The discussion is of the Middle East within the post-911 political/military/social sphere. Particular focus is put upon the relationship and forced intimacy between Israelis and pPalestinians in the 18 months following the September 11 attacks.
      Israel |x Arabs.; Israel.; United States -- Foreign Relations -- Israel; Mishal, Nissim, 1949-
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 52)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:53-9:54)
    - People, Technology, Literature. A Lecture by Richard Poirier, November 4, 1982; cuid4157; 1 audiocassettes 34:13
      Author and literary critic Richard Poirier delivers a lecture entitled "People, Technology, Literature" or "If they don't buy the appliance, give them the literature." He discusses technology as an instrument of loss in literature. The recording starts without introduction or preamble.
      American literature -- 20th century.; Literature.; Technology.; English literature.; Literature/literary criticism; Poirier, Richard
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 53)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:1)
    - Racial Rival as American Ritual. A Conversation with Derrick Bell, February 1996; cuid4158; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 70 minutes
      After introductions from the audience, the moderator briefly eulogizes poet Joseph Brodsky, a founding member of NYIH, who had passed away the previous week. She reads a statement about him and this is followed by one more short eulogy of him entitled "In Remembrance of Joseph Brodsky, Institute Fellow," written by Carl Schorske and read by Jerry Seigel. Derrick Bell is the primary speaker, beginning his talk about 8 minutes into the recording. Professor Bell speaks briefly and generally about the subject "racial rival as American ritual" and engages with the audience.
      Race discrimination.; Race relations.; Race discrimination -- United States.; Race relations -- United States.; Race.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Schorske, Carl E.; Bell, Derrick A., 1930-2011; Seigel, Jerrold E.; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 55)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:3)
    - The Future of the United States Aerospace Industry. A Lecture by Neil deGrasse Tyson, circa 2002; cuid4159; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 57 minutes
      Neil DeGrasse Tyson discusses his work on the Commission on the Future of the United States Aerospace Industry and the report the Commission produced, entitled "Anyone, Anything, Anywhere, Anytime." The commission sought to find the reasons behind the decline in the American aerospace industry and suggestions on how to reverse the negative trend.
      Aerospace industries; Tyson, Neil deGrasse; Commission on the Future of the United States Aerospace Industry
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 56)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:4)
    - Readings and Discussion with Poet John Hollander, circa mid-1980s; cuid4160; 1 audiocassettes Approx 80 minutes; Probably put with the wrong tape, the insert (which came from a Scoth Highlander 90 minute cassette) is labeled "Question of Progress II (tape 1)"
      Recorded on both sides of a TDK D90 Normal Position audiocassette, made between 1982 and 1984
      John Hollander, reads recent (some unpublished) short poetry and invites the audience to ask questions and and spark discussion between poems.
      American poetry -- 20th century.; Poetry.; Hollander, John. Poems. Selections; American poetry -- 20th century -- History and criticism.; Hollander, John
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 57)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:5-10:6)
    - "Kid Culture," A Sexuality, Gender and Consumerism Seminar talk by David Nasaw (Tape 2), Undated; cuid4161; 1 audiocassettes 18:37
      Recording is the last 18 minutes of David Nasaw's "Sexuality, Gender, and Consumerism Seminar" discussion on Kid Culture. He discusses middle class verus working class children in the early 20th century, focusing on childrens roles in newspaper sales and home delivery.
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 58)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:7)
    - Current Practice in Law School Education. A Discussion with David A.J. Richards and Others, February 12, 1986; cuid4162; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 47 minutes; Tape Label: Burns - Richards 2/12. The audio is primarily in the left channel with poor quality due to the distant placement of the microphone from the primary speakers.
      Recorded on a BASF LH-EI 90 audiocassette (circa 1985). Side 2 is blank.
      Discussion and criticism of current practice in law school education. One speaker is NYU Professor of Law David A.J. Burns; the other is identified on the tape label only as "Burns." In the course of conversation it is learned that he attended Yale Law School in the 1960s.
      Law schools -- United States.; Law teachers -- Cambridge (Mass.); Lawyer.; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States.; Law |x Study and teaching.; Law -- United States.; Law.; Richards, David A.J.; New York University. School of Law
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 60)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:24)
    - Lecture on Post-911 Military Action by Richard Falk, circa 2002 - 2003; cuid4163; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes
      Prolific writer on issues of war, legal theory, and global relations, Richard Falk discusses the current situation in American conflicts in the Arab world. He also discusses the controversy he encountered after publishing a piece in The Nation, in which he endorsed a military response against the Taliban in Afganistan in response to the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001.
      September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Afghan War, 2001-; Falk, Richard A., 1930-
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 62)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:9-10:10)
    - Necessity, Validity and Opportunities of Culturally Specific Institutions. A Lecture by Thelma Golden, circa 2000-2010; cuid4164; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 60 minutes; Moderate electronic hum from the source tape heard throughout on both sides.
      Thelma Golden poses and discusses the question, "What is the necessity, validity and opportunities for a culturally specific institution?" Depending on the year of this recording, Golden is speaking either as the Deputy Director for Exhibitions and Programs (2000-2005) or Director and President (2005-present) of the Studio Museum in Harlem.
      African American art museum curators; African American art; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Golden, Thelma; Studio Museum in Harlem
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 63)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:11)
    - Breaking Open the Head. A Discussion with Daniel Pinchbeck about His Recent Book, November 2, 2002; cuid4165; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 60 minutes
      Open City founding editor Daniel Pinchbeck discusses his recently published book, Breaking Open the Head. The book explores Pinchbeck's experimentation of psychodelic drugs and world travels, cultural criticism, and philosophy. Q&A after about 35 minutes.
      Literature/literary criticism; Literature.; Avant-garde literature.; American literature -- 21st century; Pinchbeck, Daniel
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 64)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:12)
    - Travels with Herodotus. A Discussion with Ryszard Kapuscinski, circa 2004; cuid4166; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 60 minutes
      Ryszard Kapuscinski discusses his work writing about Herodotus. Asked to write a textbook on journalistic reportage, Kapuscinski decided to do it through the lens of an examination of Herodotus, whom he considers to be the best author of reportage in history. The discussion is on Herodotus as the first globalist and his understanding that in order to understand one's own culture's history, one must also try to understand the history of other cultures as well. The book, Travels with Herodotus, was published in 2004.
      Literature |x History and criticism.; History.; History -- Study and teaching; History and criticism.; Writing history; Greek history; Travel journalism; Journalism; Reportage literature; Herodotus; Kapuściński, Ryszard
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 65)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:13)
    - European Response to September 11. A Lecture by Jane Kramer, circa early 2002; cuid4167; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes
      European correspondent for the New Yorker, Jane Kramer discusses the European response to September 11 from both historical and contemporary aspects.
      New Yorker (New York, N.Y.: 1925); September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Kramer, Jane
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 66)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:14-10:15)
    - Translating the Poetry of Eugenio Montale. A Discussion with Jonathan Galassi, 2002; cuid4168; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 56 minutes; Sound quality is poor; Loud electronic hum throughout both sides of recording.
      President and Publisher of Farrar, Straus and Giroux, Jonathan Galassi discusses the life and poetry of Eugenio Montale, and his own work in translating those poems into English.
      Lyric poetry; Poetry -- Translating; Italian poetry; Poetry.; Galassi, Jonathan; Montale, Eugenio, 1896-1981
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 67)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:16)
    - A Warning about Good Things. A Discussion with David Rieff, 2002; cuid4169; 2 audiocassettes Approx. 90 minutes; Tape 2 audio in left channel only
      Recorded on three sides of two audio cassettes; Side 2 of tape 2 is blank
      David Rieff presents a thumbnail sketch the humanitatrian emergencies such as wars and disasters he has witnessed and written about over the last 10 years. Recently dubbed "Mr. Pessimism" by Time magazine, Rieff tries to offer, not so much pessimism, but "a warning about good things." He argues against the dangerous assumption that "all good things go together."
      The second tape was previously thought to be a separate intellectual entity and given its own unique identifier: ref2325. The preservation master and access copy for that tape is labeled as such.
      War stories, Bosnian; Sarajevo (Bosnia and Hercegovina); Humanitarian assistance; Humanitarianism; Rieff, David
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 68)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:17-10:18)
    - Media Unlimited: How the Torrent of Images and Sounds Overwhelms Our Lives. A Conversation with Todd Gitlin, 2002; cuid4170; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 46 minutes
      Todd Gitlin speaks on the subject of his new book, Media Unlimited: How the Torrent of Images and Sounds Overwhelms Our Lives.
      Mass media.; Internet |z United States.; Gitlin, Todd
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 70)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:19)
    - Discussion on Writing with Novelist Jennifer Egan, 2002; cuid4171; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 60 minutes
      Writer Jennifer Egan discusses her writing process and several of her novels, the most recent of which, Look At Me, published on September 18, 2001, was about Muslim terrorism with a protagonist errily similar to Mohammad Atta, one of the ringleaders and hijackers of teh September 11 attacks.
      Writing; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Fiction.; Egan, Jennifer; Atta, Mohamed, 1968-2001
      - Original Recording (Box 72, Audiocassette 71)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 113, Cd 10:20)
    - The Importance of Truth and Reconciliation. A Lecture by Albie Sachs, February 2002; cuid4172; 1 audiocassettes Approx. 60 minutes